- Hey everyone, James Rath here.
So recently I've been seeing
some articles that say
Facebook helps the blind see images.
Now, I put quotations over see because
obviously this isn't 100% accurate,
these are just sort of click-baity titles.
But Facebook has taken another step to
sort of push accessibility for its users,
which is actually really cool.
But it's still not quite there yet,
from what they want it to be.
So this feature that I've talking about
that Facebook just rolled out
is allowing the voice readers in
iPhone and Mac, no, not Mac,
I think it's just on iOS.
So this feature that Facebook rolled out
is basically a addition to
just allowing your voiceover
on your iPhone and iPad
reading other posts and,
everything that's on the
screen on the Facebook app.
But now it will actually try to describe
what's in the images
that your friends share
that are uploaded to Facebook
by pages and what not.
So the way that Facebook
is describing this feature
is that artificial intelligence
will be able to sort of
scan the image and tell you
how many people are in the image
and if there's a rainforest,
if it's trees, if it's an ocean,
if it's a road, what is in this image.
It's not perfect, I've tried it myself.
In fact, it's not even that good yet.
But I went through and I
had it read all of my like
Instagram pictures and some were like
beaches, some were skies and
it just wasn't able to recognize that,
it wasn't able to recognize a dog.
But it, what it was able to recognize is
how many people were in an image.
So that was kinda cool,
but then I thought about.
You know, Facebook already can tell
with its artifical intelligence,
how many people are in an image.
What I mean by that is whenever
I'm uploading a picture to
Facebook and say it's a
group of my friends and I.
Image is posted, it's asking me like
who do you want to tag in this image.
It's already able to sort
of recognize the faces.
Now not only can it
recognize what a face is but
it already knows like who is Mike,
and it knows who is Matt,
and who's, I'm just
saying random names here.
But it already knows who my friends are,
based on their face and,
that's a little creepy,
it's cool in a way,
but it's a thing and Facebook
has had that for years now.
But now it just sort of narrates that.
So maybe other users have had success
where it's able to describe like
a beach or maybe it's just the most
simplistic photos that it
can sort of read objects of.
But as of yet, I still
cannot get it to read
any more or describe any more than just
how many people are in an image.
But enough talking about
it, let's go demonstrate it.
So when you have the built-in
voiceover on iOS turned on,
it will narrate everything
that you're doing on screen.
This is specifically helpful for those
who are blind or visually impaired.
(iPhone voiceover)
So this is a public
Facebook page here for a public figure.
(iPhone English and
foreign language voiceover)
Also shows you that voiceover
can change its language
when it's reading different
languages, which is cool.
- [iPhone] Image may
contain one person, smiling.
- [James] So that's the A.I. of Facebook,
being able to tell if it's
outdoors, if it's nature,
so that's actually really cool.
It was only able to tell one person,
it wasn't able to
recognize the other face.
- [iPhone] Image may contain eight people,
outdoor, water, nature
- [James] So with this next image here,
this one was unable to recognize
that it was a dog and a cat,
and that it was outdoors and nature.
The image description that's narrating was
actually manually put in by
the uploader of the image.
Facebook wasn't the only social network
to extend accessibility reach,
and what I mean is Twitter
has also rolled out
a feature that allows
you to have more than
140 characters in a tweet with an image,
but you can't actually see the text.
What it is is, you can add an extra
420 characters I believe,
and you can use that to describe
what your image that you're uploading
for those of us who are
visually impaired or blind.
Though you can't actually read this text,
it's sort of, it's an alternate text
that's in the image file,
I don't know, it's technical terms.
Anyway, it's invisible text that is there,
but the invisible text can be picked up
and read by screen readers,
by voiceover on iOS,
and the iPad and iPhone.
So, I'm gonna demonstrate for you
how to upload an image
and add the image description,
and then how to get it to read it to you.
Let's do that now.
When you're in the Twitter app,
you go to the gear/settings
in your profile section.
And then you click on Display and sounds,
and then Accessibility at the bottom.
Then make sure that you
have the toggle on for
Compose image descriptions.
Once you add that, when you
go to compose your tweet,
select the image that you
want from your library,
and then make your tweet out,
if you're even gonna
tweet anything with it.
Now to add the description of the image
you tap on add description,
then you can either paste text,
you can type it or use dictation.
In this case I decided
to just take the text
I already had from Instagram and
copy and paste it for the same image.
So make sure everything's alright,
then you hit add.
Once you make all the final
adjustments to your image,
whether it's edit or what not,
you just hit the send tweet,
refresh and, there it is.
So now when we enable voiceover.
- [iPhone] Enable voiceover.
- [James] Which you can do through Siri or
in the settings under Accessibility.
- [iPhone/Siri] @jamesrath, This is Pal.
This was the very first
dog I grew up with.
She passed away a few years ago.
She was the sweetest.
- [James] So it reads the tweet.
- [iPhone/Siri] Image. Image description,
a husky dog laid down in the snow.
- [James] And then it
successfully reads the
invisible text caption that
you added to the image.
- [iPhone/Siri] Her bright
brown eyes look into the camera.
- So this whole video has kinda been about
image descriptions and it's
something that I'm going to try
to do now on Instagram, Tumblr,
for my own original work.
It's something that's
important to people who have
screen readers or braille readers.
It's important if you
want your content to be
reaching a broader audience,
if you don't want to exclude people.
It's good to add image descriptions,
just add a sentence, two, three sentences
depending on what your
context is in the image.
And just sorta describe
what is happening in the picture that
you're trying to share with the world.
So it's cool that Twitter
is now allowing that,
for when you upload an
image to the iPhone app.
It's also important that you add 'em on
Instagram, Facebook, Tumblr,
wherever you're sharing it.
There's some do's and don'ts
for image descriptions
and if you just want the best practices,
I'll have a link down below to
get you sort of started on that
because I'm still learning how to do it.
I'm just trying to figure out, you know.
And it does help me sort of figure out
how do I describe this?
Like how would I describe
what is happening here?
So it's interesting, makes
me think a little bit,
it's a learning experience.
So that's fun.
But yeah, I just kinda wanna talk about
images desrciptions, what they were and
how they can benefit people
and why you should as a content
creator or content sharer
include your image descriptions.
If you haven't seen last week's video,
I'm also trying to campaign for Youtube to
add the ability for creators to
have audio descriptions,
so after you upload a
video and you want to
add narrations for people
who are visually impaired,
have cognitive disabilities or
just wanna have extra
context to what's happening.
Having that extra audio track that would
allow you to describe the missing pieces
that you would otherwise need to see,
what's happening in the video.
In order to get the context of
what's happening, basically.
But, there's a whole video on that
and if you wanna sort of
share and help that movement,
I've already sort of emailed it to
some guys at Youtube and
just keep sharing it,
make it a priority for them to add this.
Check out that video.
Anyway guys, thanks so much
for watching this week's video,
I hope you guys enjoyed and I got
so much more content.
I'm gonna be at Playlist Live,
if you guys don't know what that is,
it's a convention in Orlando, Florida
that's happening April, days
are gonna be right there.
I can't remember the dates.
I should probably know,
considering I'm going to be there.
I need to take a flight, yeah.
I'm gonna be there though, if
you guys want to meet there,
I'm happy to meet with you guys
and say hi, take a selfie,
and just have a cool conversation.
That's what these booths are about.
Leave a comment down below
if we want to start that conservation,
we could finish it in person,
we could finish it in the comments,
we could finish it on Twitter
where you can follow me.
Yeah, I'm just shameless
promoting right now.
I will see you guys next time, bye.
(chill downtempo music)